David Hamburg MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
- United Nations
  - Special Adviser Francis Deng, 2007 - 2011; Relevant correspondence and meeting materials with and regarding distinguished scholar Francis Deng, the second Special Adviser to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide, spans from 2007-2011, beginning with Deng’s appointment (5/29/2007) through the strengthening of the OSAPG and Hamburg’s resignation as chairman of the AC (see materials for AC meeting of 10/29/2008). Messages between 5/30/2007 and 7/16/2007 consist mainly of introductions, orientation, and meeting plans, as Deng had not yet relocated to New York from Washington, D.C. Deng and Hamburg met with the Secretary-General’s core staff on 6/27/2007, and there was some discussion on the inclusion of the R2P mandate in the OSAPG’s activities (see correspondence dated 6/28/2007 and 7/04/2007 and a message from Special Adviser Ed Luck on 5/16/2008 about the R2P model). On 7/17/2007, Deng and Hamburg began discussing staff and budget for the Office as well as a meeting of the Advisory Committee in early September and subsequent messages relate to the planning and follow-up of the meeting. In early 2008, Hamburg suggested potential staff members for the OSAPG (1/19, 3/07, 3/13, 4/25, and 5/01, 2008) and invited Deng to participate in his documentary on prevention. On 5/07/2008, Deng wrote to the Advisory Committee to explain his approach to the mandate. The letter also cites his “hope to invited members of UN agencies, departments and programs … to join us in forming an on-going consultative body that would meet periodically.” UN departments and agencies weighed in on Deng’s activities at the 6/05 and 10/27/2008 meeting and recommendations were compiled for Hamburg in the 2008 document titled Recommendations to SAPG by UN Departments and Agencies. Note that meeting materials from the June 2008 meeting with UN Departments and Agencies are included with Advisory Committee materials. Deng’s approach to his mandate and various initiatives are outlined in several messages where an attachment is indicated, as well as the written work in the folder titled Deng Papers. Hamburg was helpful in the writing of several of these documents. (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on Preventing Genocide, 2005 - 2011; Dr. Hamburg was appointed as Chairman of the Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide in early 2006. Members of the committee included: Monica Andersson, Senior Adviser, Department for International Law, Human Rights and Treaty Law, Swedish Foreign Ministry; Romeo Dallaire, Canadian Senator and former Force Commander of the UN Mission for Rwanda; Gareth Evans, President, International Crisis Group and former Foreign Minister for Australia; Zakari Ibrahim, former Minister of State for Foreign Affairs of Nigeria; Juan Mendez, President, International Crisis Group; Sadako Ogata, President, Japan International Cooperation Agency and former UN High Commissioner for Refugees; and Archbishop Desmond Tutu, winner of the Nobel Peace Prize and former Chair of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission of South Africa. Relevant correspondence, meeting materials, and notes span from 2005 to 2010 and are grouped according to “landmarks” of the group, particularly Advisory Committee meetings. The folder is divided into nine subsections, and each folder contains correspondence with committee members pertaining to the topic of the folder as well as unrelated correspondence from that time period. Of particular interest is Hamburg’s correspondence with Desmond Tutu; the correspondence with Tutu grouped into the Advisory Committee folder is on a range of topics not limited to the United Nations: 2005 - Fall 2006: Appointment and First Meeting of the Advisory Committee; Fall - Winter 2006: October Meeting of the Advisory Committee; Fall 2006 - Spring 2007: Pre-Deng Appointment; Spring - Summer 2007: Appointment of Francis Deng; Spring - Fall 2007: September 2007 Meeting of the Advisory Committee; Winter 2007 - Early 2008: Consolidation of OSAPG; Spring 2008 - Early 2009: October 2008 Advisory Committee Meeting; June 2008 Meeting with UN Departments and Agencies; 2009-2010: Misc Correspondence and DAH Resignation. Hamburg’s memos to committee members provide a sense of each landmark and the progress being made with the establishment of the OSAPG. The memos dated 3/29/2006, 5/17/2006, 6/01/2006, and 8/17/2006 relate to the establishment of the committee and the first meeting. Memos dated 9/25/2006, 10/23/2006, and 12/26/2006 relate to the second meeting of the Committee and the submission of the group’s main report to the Secretary-General that included recommendations for the role of the Special Adviser and the Advisory Committee at the UN. That report is in the Fall-Winter 2006 folder entitled Meeting Materials. Memos dated 12/26/2006, 1/16/2007, 1/23/2007, 2/26/2007, 3/02/2007, 3/13/2007, and 4/09/2007 report on Hamburg’s meetings with the Secretary-General and his key staff and the progress being made in fulfilling the recommendations of the Advisory Committee report prior to the appointment of Francis Deng. Hamburg’s memos dated 5/29/2007, 5/30/3007, and 8/15/2007 announce the appointment of Francis Deng. Memos dated 7/03/2007, 10/02/2007, 10/15/2007, and 10/31/2007 relate to the planning and follow-up activities for the meeting of the Advisory Committee in September 2007. Meeting materials are included in the Spring-Fall 2007 folder. Memos dated 5/27/2008, 8/20/2008, 10/20/2008, 11/14/2008, 1/14/2009, and 2/02/2009 concern the meeting of the Advisory Committee in October 2008 and its follow-up. The final memo provides a copy of the AC report (grouped into the Meeting Materials and Report folder). The announcement of Hamburg’s resignation is noted in the report. Hamburg’s final memo to the committee is dated 6/04/2010 and reports on the Secretary-General’s determinations regarding the future of the OSAPG and the Advisory Committee. He attaches a letter from the Secretary-General on this subject. Hamburg writes, "….One of the decisions states that “The Special Adviser on the Prevention of Genocide (SAPG) and the Special Adviser (SASG) who works on implementing the Responsibility to Protect will complete their work to establish a Joint Office on the Prevention of Genocide and the Promotion of the Responsibility to Protect.” The Secretary-General also decided that “The Advisory Committee on the Prevention of Genocide will be given a new mandate, title, and composition to reflect the broader concerns of the Joint Office. Its role will be one of advocacy and awareness-raising worldwide.” The two Special Advisers have been directed by the Secretary-General to carry out pertinent consultations and make recommendations for the recomposition of the Committee. Francis Deng remains in close contact with me and I believe that both Special Advisers will maintain close consultations with us on plans for the new Advisory Committee..." (Box 1)
  - Related United Nations Initiatives, 1996 - 2006; Hamburg had involvement in several activities in addition to the establishment of the OSAPG and the Advisory Committee. Archived documents in the UN folder also include: the Ambassador’s Group for Prevention, which involved a group of Ambassadors with special interest in prevention of genocide headed by Peter Maurer of Switzerland; the Department of Economic and Social Affairs, where Hamburg worked closely with Gay Rosenblum-Kumar in participating in an Experts Group on Conflict Prevention; the Scientific Community, in which he forged a relationship between key scientific advisors and UN leadership; the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights Advisory Group, where he worked closely with UN High Commissioner Sadako Ogata; UN Institute for Training and Research, where Hamburg served on the Advisory Board for several years and worked particularly closely with Connie Peck; UPEACE, which he helped to launch; and most notably the World Health Organization Health as a Bridge to Peace initiative, including Hamburg’s direct correspondence with Gro Harlem Brundtland, Director General of the WHO. Some original correspondence with key ambassadors Sadako Ogata and Gro Harlem Brundtland and her husband Arne Olav is included in the hard copy archive. (Box 1)
    - Ambassadors Group for Prevention, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Department of Economic and Social Affairs, 1998; 2004 (Box 1)
    - Scientific Community, 1996; 2000 - 2001; 2004 (Box 1)
    - UN Development Programme, 2004 (Box 1)
    - UN High Commissioner for Human Rights Advisory, 1997 - 2001 (Box 1)
    - UN Institute for Training and Research, 1998 - 2009 (Box 1)
    - UPEACE, 2000 - 2001 (Box 1)
    - World Health Organization – Health as a Bridge to Peace, 1997 - 2006 (Box 1)
  - Research and Reports on the UN and Preventing Deadly Conflict, 1998 - 2010; This folder contains a sampling of research materials and written work pertinent to conflict prevention in the UN context. Of particular interest is an annotated copy of the 1948 Genocide Convention, Dr. Hamburg’s Case for an International Center for Genocide Prevention, and the two papers by Tapio Kanninen, who worked very diligently to implement the objectives of the PAC report. The 2009 report by William Zartman was commissioned specifically by the OSAPG to analyze identity conflicts leading to genocide, and the paper by Hamburg’s student, Allie Sharma, was completed in her capacity as a resident at Cornell with a special interest in genocide prevention. Additional writings by Dr. Hamburg are included in the larger DAH Written Work section. (Box 1)
- European Union
  - Secretary General Javier Solana and Core Staff, 2005 - 2010; Original correspondence between Hamburg and Secretary General Solana is available in the hard copy archive and grouped by year. The Solana files span from 2005 through 2010. The primary staff member grouped into the Javier Solana file is his Chief of Staff, Enrique Mora, with whom Hamburg worked closely to implement the prevention agenda in the EU. Hamburg’s work with Javier Solana and Enrique Mora with respect to prevention of deadly conflict and other mass violence is marked by several key landmarks (with corresponding documents in the archive). The primary theme of their work together (and Hamburg’s other work in the EU) is the intention to establish an EU Center for the Prevention of Genocide. Hamburg met Solana in 2005, where they discussed the CCPDC and the prevention of genocide (see letters dated 2/25 and 3/23, 2005). Hamburg facilitated a connection between Solana and President Jimmy Carter in establishing the “steering committee regarding the feasibility of the EU Center for Genocide Prevention,” in which key staff from the Carter Center participated (see letters dated 6/30/2005, 5/18/2006, and 6/23/2006). In the early stages of their interaction, a proposal for the creation of the Center was submitted (see Steering Committee folder, 2006) and Hamburg, Mora, and Solana discussed the possibility of Sweden as a host country for the Center. The majority of messages in 2006 reflect this intention, with Sweden looking less certain in December 2006 and early 2007. In his message of 3/06/2007, Hamburg expressed interest in Germany, Spain, or Ireland as potential host countries. In July of 2007, Hamburg participated in a meeting of the EUISS in Paris in which Solana played a key role and the prevention of genocide was discussed. Following that meeting, Hamburg’s relationship with the EUISS continued, and he was in regular contact with Solana and Mora regarding EUISS meetings and the potential there for implementing the prevention agenda (see messages dated 10/22/2007, 11/14/2007, and several messages in 2008 identified as re: EUISS). On 2/27/2008, Mora indicated to Hamburg that Hungary was interested in acting as the host country for the Center. Hamburg began contact with representatives from the Hungarian government in March and the contacts continued through 2010. Dr. Hamburg regularly reported on his contacts with the Hungarian government to Solana and Mora (see letters dated 3/19/2008, 4/21/2008, 5/21 and 5/23 2008, 11/03/2008, 12/19/2009, and additional letters marked “re: Hungary”). Materials related to the establishment of the Center in Hungary are included in the folder, “Establishment of Center in Hungary, 2008-2010.” 2009 messages between Hamburg an Mora/Solana primarily concern Hungary, particularly a meeting in Budapest, meetings of the EUISS, and the inclusion of Solana in Hamburg’s documentary on the prevention of genocide. 2010 correspondence with Solana and Mora concern the completion of Solana’s term, and his future positions at the Brookings Institution in Washington, D.C. and the newly established Aspen Institute in Spain. Further correspondence concerning Hungary is included in the related folders. (Box 2)
  - Steering Committee to the Secretary General on Preventing Genocide, 2005 - 2011; In early 2006, Dr. Hamburg was appointed as Chairman of a Steering Committee reporting to the Secretary General to discuss the feasibility of creating an International Center on the Prevention of Genocide. According to the group’s 2006 proposal, “Members of the Steering Committee include Ragnar Ängeby of the Folke Bernadotte Academy, Raymond Georis of the Madariaga European Foundation, Enrique Mora as Personal Representative of Javier Solana, and John Stremlau of the Carter Center. Beatrix A. Hamburg of the Social Medicine and Public Policy Program at Cornell University was a constant collaborator throughout this initiative. At its third and final meeting in Atlanta on 11-12 July 2006, the Committee benefited from the supportive presence of President Jimmy Carter, and from the insightful contribution of Gareth Evans, President and Chief Executive of the International Crisis Group.” Relevant correspondence, meeting materials, and notes span from 2005 to 2011and are grouped by year. In 2005, the group formed, and correspondence pertained to establishment of connections with Javier Solana, Jimmy Carter, and outside members such as Gareth Evans. The first Steering Committee meeting was planned for January of 2006 (see 2006 folder entitled, January 2006, First Meeting of the Steering Committee). The second committee meeting was in April, and the third meeting was in July, hosted at the Carter Center with the involvement and endorsement of Jimmy Carter. A key document, the Proposal for the Creation of an International Centre for Prevention of Genocide and Crimes against Humanity (saved in the EU Key Documents folder as well as in the Steering Committee 2006 folder) was completed in August of 2006, and much of the correspondence during the summer pertains to this proposal. Hamburg’s message of 9/05/2006 discusses Sweden in depth as a potential host country for the Center, particularly due to the strong interest of Jan Eliasson, then president of the UN General Assembly and Foreign Minister of Sweden (note that Hamburg also had interactions with Eliasson in the UN context as well as an ongoing friendship). Other messages in the fall and winter indicate that Eliasson lost the Swedish reelection as Foreign Minister, which impacted Sweden’s feasibility as a host country for the Center. Correspondence between 2007 and 2011, following the submission of the proposal to the Secretary General, concern follow-up activities to establish the Center in the EU. Raymond Georis and Ragnar Angeby were in regular contact about progress being made in their institutions, the Madariaga Foundation and the Folke Bernadotte Academy, respectively. Hamburg kept in touch about his progress at the UN and intermittent contacts with Javier Solana and other EU officials. For example, in late 2007 Dr. Hamburg met with Danilo Turk, former UN contact, who had just assumed the presidency of Slovenia, and the group briefly considered Slovenia as a host country for the Center. In the summer of 2008, it became clear that Hungary was a serious contender. (Box 2)
  - Establishment of International Centre on Preventing Genocide in Hungary, 2008 - 2010; Hamburg’s correspondence with representatives from the Hungarian government spanned between 2008 and 2010. His official contacts regarding the establishment of the Center included: Daniel Ambrus, Political Analyst, Directorate General Communication, European Commission, Brussels; Gabriel Brodi, Permanent Representative of the Republic of Hungary to the UN; Istvan Lakatos, Ambassador at Large for Human Rights, Hungarian Foreign Ministry; Viktor Polgar, Consul General of Hungary; and Gyorgy Tatar, Head of Unit, Horizontal Security Affairs, Conflict Prevention and Human Rights Task Force, Council of the EU. Of these contacts, Hamburg worked most closely with Istvan Lakatos. Preparations for the establishment of the International Centre on Prevention of Genocide in Hungary began with Hamburg’s correspondence with Daniel Ambrus and Gyorgy Tatar. In the early correspondence between 3/14/2008 and June 2008, it is indicated that Hamburg had met Ambrus and Tatar at an EUISS meeting in Paris and that Ambrus and Tatar had additional meetings with representatives from the steering committee (including Ragnar Angeby and contacts at the Madariaga Foundation) as well as with Enrique Mora regarding the Center. In his message of 3/14/2008, Ambrus indicated that the Hungarian government was “interested to explore the feasibility of the center” and “investigating the possibilities” and that Ambrus would be preparing a report for the Hungarian Prime Minister’s consideration. Hamburg and Ambrus were then in close contact, and on 6/02/2008 Hamburg shared insight on how a Center could be established, including leadership with a close relationship and knowledge of the EU and UN systems and prioritization of appointments and “pillars of prevention” that would be covered. In his message of 7/28/2008, Ambrus wrote, “Following the request of the Cabinet of the Prime Minister the Foreign Ministry of the Republic of Hungary has agreed to assign the Head of the Human Rights Department, Mr. István Lakatos to coordinate the efforts on looking into the feasibility of setting up the Center” and that a brainstorming meeting would be held on September 3rd in Hungary. Substantive correspondence with Lakatos begins in September of 2008, particularly in their correspondence between 9/08/2008 and 9/11/2008. Lakatos sent a concept note regarding the center to Hamburg on 10/08/2008, and Hamburg made key suggestions in his message of 10/10/2008 about adding a section on “illustrative tools” for preventing genocide. Lakatos visited New York in November, and Hamburg connected him with contacts at the UN as well as informing him of key initiatives and departments in the interest of “EU-UN collaboration in this field” (see message of 10/23/2008). On June 25-26, 2009, Hamburg participated in the Second Human Rights Forum at the Foreign Ministry in Hungary, in which the International Center was a key agenda item (see materials in the 2009 Second Human Rights Forum folder). Messages between February and July of 2009 involve preparation and follow-up for this meeting. In July and August of 2009, Hamburg and Lakatos corresponded about a potential relationship between the U.S. Government and the Hungarian Center, most notably through a series of hearings at the Senate Foreign Relations Committee proposed by Hamburg to the Committee Chairs, Senators John Kerry and Richard Lugar (this proposal is included in the DAH Written Work: Lectures and Key Documents folder, entitled PMV as an Organizing Principle of American Foreign Policy). On 3/12/2010, Lakatos sent Hamburg an invitation to the official launching ceremony of the Budapest Foundation for the International Prevention of Genocide and Mass Atrocities, where the Deed of Foundation would be signed. Later that month, the launch ceremony was postponed due to “technical problems.” On 9/09/2010, Lakatos wrote again to announce the launch ceremony “on 18 October within the framework of the Third Budapest Human Rights Forum.” Important documents on the establishment of the EU Center are included in the Key EU documents folder. (Box 2)
  - Related European Union Initiatives, 2003 - 2010; Hamburg’s EU activities have primarily concerned the establishment of the Center. In conjunction with his work to promote the prevention of mass violence and establish the Center, Hamburg attended relevant conferences in Sweden in 2003 and 2004 and participated extensively in meetings of the European Union Institute for Security Studies between 2007 and 2010. Hamburg served as a panelist on preventing genocide at several meetings of the EUISS, as well as serving as a key advisor to EUISS president, Alvaro de Vasconcelos. Related correspondence and meeting materials for Hamburg’s trips to Sweden and his work with the EUISS are included in this folder. (Box 2)
    - 2003 Trip to Sweden (Box 2)
    - 2004 Stockholm International Forum (Box 2)
    - EU Institute for Security Studies, 2003 - 2010 (Box 2)
  - Key EU Documents on Preventing Genocide, 2007 - 2010; This folder contains a sampling of research materials and written work pertinent to conflict prevention in the EU context. Of particular interest are the key documents on the Establishment of the Hungarian Centre, Dr. Hamburg’s 2008 Illustrative Tools for Preventing Mass Violence, and the paper Hamburg coauthored with Alexander George on The Promise of the European Union for the Prevention of Genocide. Two governmental papers are also included: the 2006 EU Council Document on Prevention and the EU Programme for Prevention of Violent Conflicts. (Box 2)
- Scholars and World Leaders
  - Condoleezza Rice and George W. Bush, 1996 - 2005; Hamburg’s relationship with Condoleezza Rice began in the 1990s at Stanford University, where Rice served as Provost and Professor of Political Science. Their relationship continued after she was appointed National Security Advisor then Secretary of State in the Bush Administration. A highlight of the correspondence in this archive are the documents dated 11/09 and 12/18, 2001, when Hamburg worked with Senators Nunn and Lugar, former Secretary William Perry, and others to propose a “Bush-Putin Initiative against Catastrophic Terrorism.” The group met with Rice in late 2001 to urge the Bush Administration to adopt important protections against future nuclear, biological, and other terrorism in the future. (Box 3)